Wow!
天啊
-Well then, let's dig in. -I'm digging in!
-那麼我們開動吧 -我開動了
The food today's great as usual!
今天的菜也一樣好吃
Well...
天啊
Mita.
三田小姐
We're really lucky, aren't we?
我們真的很幸福，對吧？
We get to eat delicious food every day.
每天都能吃到這麼美味的菜餚
Mommy. Let's go to the amusement park together again!
媽媽，我們下次再一起去遊樂園玩吧
Right. Let's go, Akari.
就這麼辦，我們一起去吧
Mita. Could you teach me how to cook next time?
三田小姐，下次可以教我做菜嗎？
I've been slacking on it since I always relied on Mom to cook.
我總是依賴媽媽做菜，沒有認真學習
Oh, you can't?
不可以嗎？
That's not it. As you wish.
可以，我知道了
All right! Thanks.
太好了，謝謝妳
Are you all right?
你沒事吧？
You're so gross!
你真噁心
Man, someone must be talking behind my back again.
真是的，一定又有人在我背後說壞話
Are you sure you didn't catch a cold?
你確定你不是感冒了嗎？
That's not possible.
那是不可能的事
Seconds, please!
請再給我一碗飯
Seconds please, Mita.
三田小姐，請再給我一碗飯
Yes.
是
Mita, could it be that you were spacing out just now?
難道妳剛才在發呆嗎，三田小姐？
I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
That's our first time seeing that!
我們第一次看見這樣的妳
You don't look too well.
妳的臉色看起來不太好
Please let us know if you feel sick.
若身體不適，請告訴我們
No, I'm fine.
沒事，我很好
I still think Mita should eat with us.
我還是覺得三田小姐 應該跟我們一起吃飯
Kii's right. If you just stand there,
希衣說得對，妳一直站在那裡
I feel a little restless.
我感到有些不安
I'm a housekeeper, so I do not intend on eating with everyone in the family.
我是家政婦 因此我不打算和大家一起吃飯
I believe I have emphasized earlier.
我相信我之前已經強調過這一點了
Hey, what does "emphasize" mean?
“強調”是什麼意思？
It means she made a promise.
表示她承諾了這件事
Mita, please don't say that!
三田小姐，不要說那種話
Just let her be, Kii. Mita's working right now.
別煩三田小姐了，希衣 她現在正在工作
You don't need to sulk like that.
妳別生悶氣了
What's wrong, Kaito?
怎麼了，海斗？
It's nothing serious, but we have parents' day soon.
沒什麼大不了的事 只是學校即將舉辦教學參觀日
What? When is it?
什麼？什麼時候？
This coming Wednesday.
這個星期三
-Can you come, Dad? -Oh...
-你可以來參加嗎？爸爸 -這…
Sorry, but I don't think so.
對不起，我應該無法參加
-I just joined the new company, so... -I guessed so.
-我才剛進一家新公司，所以… -我猜也是如此
Kai. Why don't you ask Mita to go instead?
小斗，你可以請三田小姐去參加
What?
什麼？
Will you?
妳願意去嗎？
I believe I've emphasized it, too.
我相信我也強調過這一點了
I am not your family member.
我不是你們的家人
Then, could you write on the form that you'll be absent, Dad?
那麼你可以在表格上 填寫你會缺席嗎，爸爸？
Got it. Sorry. Kaito.
可以，對不起，海斗
Don't worry about it.
沒關係
Maybe you're better off not coming.
或許你不去反而比較好
What? What do you mean, Kaito?
什麼？什麼意思，海斗？
My teacher wants us to write a letter of appreciation to our mothers
我的班導師要求大家 寫一封給媽媽的感謝信
and read them out during parents' day.
並在教學參觀日朗讀這封信
What? Then, what about the kids with no moms?
什麼？那沒有媽媽的孩子怎麼辦？
He said we could just write it to our fathers,
他說可以寫一封給爸爸的感謝信
but it doesn't sit well with me.
但我還是覺得難以接受
Why did your teacher come up with such an insensitive assignment?
你的班導師怎麼會出這種 不顧他人感受的作業？
What will you do, Kai?
你要怎麼辦，小斗？
I'm really at a loss right now.
我不知道，真的很煩惱
But, I feel like there should be a good solution to this.
不過我總覺得應該會有好的解決辦法
Thanks.
謝謝妳
This is the Asuda residence.
這裡是阿須田家
Oh, this is Yuki. Is Kii around?
我是結城，希衣在嗎？
One moment.
請稍等
Hold on. I need to talk to you, too.
等一下，我也有事要跟妳說
What is it?
有什麼事嗎？
Did you hear about anything from Urara?
妳有沒有從小麗那裡聽到什麼事？
What do you mean?
什麼意思？
Ever since you went back to the family,
自從妳回到那個家之後
she said that she will never visit that home again.
她就說她再也不會去那裡了
Also...
而且…
when she hated the idea so much.
現在卻說她要開始相親
Do you know anything?
妳是否知道內情？
I think I'm in love with Keiichi.
我想我愛上姐夫了
No, I don't.
我不知道
I see.
好吧
I will let Kii take the call.
我請希衣來聽電話
It's a call from your grandfather.
這是妳外公打來的電話
Hello, Grandpa?
喂？外公？
Yes.
是
Really? Okay!
真的嗎？我知道了
Thank you! See you!
謝謝你，再見
What's the matter, Kii?
什麼事，希衣？
Grandpa said that
外公說
since I'm attending elementary school next year,
我明年就要上小學了
we should go buy my school bag together.
所以他要帶我去買書包
Already? Grandpa is getting way too excited.
這麼早就買？外公太過興奮了
You should join me, Mita.
三田小姐也跟我們一起去吧
I believe I have made myself clear.
我相信我已經說得很清楚了
I will not go out with--
我不會和你們出門…
Then, just treat this as an order!
那麼就算是工作命令吧
Please!
求求妳
As you wish.
我知道了
I like this one, Grandpa.
外公，我喜歡這一個
Which one, as it were?
哪一個呢？
Which one's better, Mita?
哪一個比較好，三田小姐？
That is...
這件事…
Don't say that. Tell us what you think, as it were.
別這麼說，告訴我們妳的想法吧
Please! You can just point at one, as it were!
拜託，妳用手指指一下吧
Which do you think looks nice, Mommy?
哪一個比較好，媽媽？
Well, I think this one's better.
爸爸覺得這個比較好
What? This one's better, right Mommy?
什麼？這個比較好，對吧，媽媽？
What's wrong, Mita?
怎麼了，三田小姐？
Are you feeling unwell?
身體不舒服嗎？
No, it's nothing.
沒有，我沒事
Wow! I'll try it, too.
好厲害，我也來試試
Mita...
三田小姐…
I'm feeling the chills. Do you have ginger tea?
我覺得很冷，妳有薑茶嗎？
I do.
有
Kakeru. I think you caught a cold.
小翔，你應該是感冒了
Shut up.
閉嘴
You're going to spread it to everyone. Why don't you go sleep?
真是的，你會傳染給大家，去睡覺吧
I know.
我知道
Mita. Is my school bag too big?
三田小姐，我的書包會太大嗎？
It's fine. You will grow, Kii.
沒關係，妳會長大，希衣
Then, Mita. Come to my school opening ceremony, okay?
那麼妳來參加我的開學典禮，好嗎？
Is that...
這件事…
Just treat it as an order!
就算是工作命令吧
As you wish.
我知道了
Thanks!
謝謝妳
Kii, the bag's going to get dirtied, so put it away.
希衣，書包會弄髒的，先收起來吧
Okay!
好
Which do you think looks nice, Mommy?
哪一個比較好，媽媽？
Oh... Are you all right? Wait, where's the band-aid?
天啊，妳還好嗎？ 等一下，OK繃在哪裡？
It's fine. I brought some with me.
沒關係，我帶了OK繃
Thank you.
謝謝妳
It's my first time seeing you mess up.
我第一次見到妳出差錯
Mita! Could you help me clean my ear?
三田小姐，請幫我清耳朵
As you wish.
我知道了
Kii, you're acting too spoiled.
希衣，妳像個被寵壞的孩子
Mita's not your mom.
三田小姐不是媽媽
I know.
我知道
Mita.
三田小姐
Can you solve this question?
妳會解這個問題嗎？
The circumference X is the sum of the circumferences of the three circles.
圓周X是三個圓的圓周之和
Therefore, (6 + 4 x 2) x 3.14 = 43.96.
因此，4乘以2，加6，再乘以3.14
Oh, I see.
原來如此
Hey. Could you teach me when you're free? When you have free time, that is.
妳不忙時，願意教我功課嗎？ 只在妳有空閒的時候
As you wish.
我知道了
Thanks.
謝謝
Hey, Kaito.
喂，海斗
Have you decided what to write for the letter of appreciation?
你已經決定怎麼寫那封感謝信了嗎？
Not yet.
還沒有
I think it's probably the best to write something about Mom, but...
我覺得寫有關媽媽的事 可能還是最好的方式，不過…
But she killed herself.
不過她是自殺的
There's no way I can write it and ask
我沒辦法寫這封信
why she abandoned us to die alone.
問她丟下我們選擇自殺的原因
But, that's also what I wanted to ask Mom the most.
然而這卻是我最想問媽媽的問題
Hey. What do you think I should do, Mita?
妳認為我該怎麼辦，三田小姐？
That is...
這件事…
something you should decide for yourself, Kaito.
應該由你自己決定，海斗
Guessed as much.
我猜也是這樣
Thanks...
謝謝
"TO MOM"
（致媽媽）
"TO DAD"
（致爸爸）
Do you need any help?
你需要幫助嗎？
Oh... No, I'm fine.
不用了，我沒事
I'm home.
我回來了
Welcome home.
你回來了
Oh, sorry that I'm back late.
抱歉，這麼晚才回來
I will prepare dinner now.
我立刻去準備晚餐
Don't worry about it. It's way past your clock-out time.
不用了，已經過了妳的下班時間
It's fine, I just need to heat it up.
沒關係，晚餐只需要加熱而已
PARENTS' DAY ATTENDANCE FORM I WILL ATTEND/NOT ATTEND THE EVENT.
（教學參觀日出席表 我會參加或不參加此活動）
Thanks. Where are the kids?
謝謝，孩子們在哪裡？
Yui is reading a book to Kii,
小結朗讀書給希衣聽
but she's sleepy and fell asleep as well.
可是她自己也睏了 結果和希衣一起睡著了
Kakeru has a fever of 38 degrees Celscius,
小翔發燒到38度
and it seems like he's having a serious sore throat,
而且他的喉嚨好像痛得很厲害
so I think he should visit the hospital tomorrow.
因此我認為他明天應該去醫院看看
Then, what about Kaito?
那麼海斗呢？
He is still working on that assignment.
還在做之前的那個作業
I see.
我知道了
All right. Thank you for the food.
好，那我開動了
Your food helps me relax, as usual.
妳的飯菜如往常般，能讓我好好放鬆
Thank you, Mita.
三田小姐，謝謝妳
If there is nothing else,
要是沒有其他事情的話
I will excuse myself now.
我就先告辭了
Please excuse me.
告辭了
Excuse me. Can I ask you something?
不好意思，可以問妳一件事嗎？
What is it?
什麼事？
Do you wear that down jacket everyday?
妳每天都穿那件羽絨外套嗎？
Yes.
是的
Isn't it hot during the summer?
在夏天穿不是很熱嗎？
I don't really mind.
我不在意
Then, what about your watch and bag?
那麼手錶和手提包呢？
Oh, sorry. It's just that your attire isn't really feminine,
抱歉，只是妳的打扮不是很女性化
so I've been curious about it.
所以我一直感到好奇
Please excuse me.
我告辭了
I'm home. Sorry that I'm home late.
我回來了，抱歉，這麼晚才回來
We had an urgent case right before I was about to knock off.
今天在我下班前來了一位急診病人
-Welcome home! -I'm home!
-你回來了 -我回來了
Thanks for the watch, Daddy!
謝謝你送我手錶，爸爸
All the kids in school were envious of me!
幼稚園的小朋友們都很羨慕我
You have to cherish it, okay?
你要好好珍惜，好嗎？
Mommy was angry and said that you're too young to have one.
媽媽很生氣 她說你還太小，不能戴這種手錶
Okay! By the way, we bought this hat for you, Mommy!
好
Mita! Are you all right?
三田小姐，妳沒事吧？
Mita. Are you feeling unwell?
三田小姐，妳身體不舒服嗎？
No, I'm fine.
沒有，我沒事
But you seem to be acting strange, especially since you came back.
可是妳的行為似乎有點反常 尤其是在妳回來這裡之後
-Please excuse me. -Mita!
-我告辭了 -三田小姐
I'm embarrassed to say this,
說起來有點難為情
but I raised her alone,
她是由我獨力扶養長大的
so I couldn't do anything for her.
所以我能替她做的事不多
I don't know if you will like her.
我不知道你們是否會喜歡她
Excuse me...
請問…
Do you go on diets, Ms. Urara?
妳是否會節食？麗小姐
Oh, I don't gain weight no matter how much I eat.
我不論吃多少，體重都不會增加
Then, what kind of man do you like?
那麼妳喜歡什麼類型的男性？
Let's see...
這…
Someone that will bring me misfortune.
我喜歡可以帶給我不幸的人
What?
什麼？
Oh... What she meant was that
是這樣的…她的意思是
her only good point is her optimistic disposition,
她唯一的優點就是有樂觀的個性
so she can endure it when the going gets tough.
所以面對艱辛的情況，她都能忍受
I see!
原來如此
Then, what kind of family do you want after you get married?
那麼妳結婚之後 希望組織什麼樣的家庭？
For now...
就目前而言
I'm fine so long as I don't give birth to four children
只要不是像我姐姐那樣
and end up committing suicide, like my older sister.
生下四個小孩之後自殺就行了
Hey! They don't need any details!
喂，他們不需要知道這些細節
Why not? It's better if we're honest.
有什麼關係？還是先老實說比較好
Please excuse me.
打擾一下
There's a lipstick stain on this wine glass.
這個酒杯上有口紅印
What's going on? Isn't this a first-class hotel?
怎麼回事？這裡不是一流的飯店嗎？
I'm really sorry. I will have it replaced now--
真的很抱歉，我馬上替妳換酒杯…
Never mind, I'm used to this.
算了，我已經習慣了這種情況
Do you always speak your mind, Ms. Urara?
妳的個性是有話直說嗎，麗小姐？
Not really. If I had to compare, I guess my personality would be like this coaster.
不盡然，若要我形容的話 我的個性就像這個杯墊
I always get ignored,
總是被忽視
and I keep following people when even I'm not needed.
即使別人不需要我，我還是緊緊跟隨
She's too nervous that she got drunk, as it were!
她太緊張了，所以喝醉了吧
YUKI RESIDENCE
（結城家）
Here.
拿去
What's up with your attitude back there?
妳剛才那種態度是怎麼回事？
You're being rude to the other party.
那樣對另一方很失禮
Who cares?
有什麼關係？
It's better for them to know my real self rather than getting disappointed later!
與其讓他們以後失望 不如先讓他們認識真正的我
What is it?
怎麼了？
I think...
我覺得…
What?
什麼？
You're in love with that man, right?
妳果然還是喜歡那個男人吧？
Who are you talking about?
你指的是哪個男人？
You know who it is!
妳很清楚是誰
Are you referring to Keiichi?
難道你指的是姐夫？
Of course not!
那是不可能的事
Besides, you'll definitely be against it even if it were true.
就算真的有那種事，你也一定會反對
You can't let both of your daughters be taken away by the same man.
你不可能讓同一個男人 奪走你的兩個女兒
-Morning. -Good morning.
-早安
-See you later! -Sure, at the classroom. Bye.
-回頭見 -好，我們在教室見，再見
-One, two...
-一、二…
Ready, set! One, two, three, four...
預備，開始，一、二、三、四
-five, six... -Five, six...
-五、六
-seven, eight. Let's go! -Yes!
-七、八，繼續前進 -是
-One, two...
-一、二…
-Good morning.
-早安
Urara!
小麗
Is it true that you went on a blind date?
妳真的去相親了嗎？
Yeah. He's quite nice. He seems interested in me, too.
真的，他是個很好的人 似乎也對我感興趣
What? So, are you going to get married?
什麼？那麼妳要結婚了嗎？
Then what about school?
可是學校怎麼辦？
Well...
這…
I was thinking about quitting.
我打算辭職
Students and parents dislike me,
反正學生們和家長們都不喜歡我
and the other teachers often say that
而且其他的老師經常告訴我
I'm not suitable to be a teacher.
我不適合當老師
Are you really fine with that?
這樣真的好嗎？
It's better for you and the kids too.
對妳和妳家的孩子們也比較好
I told Mita about it.
我已經告訴過三田小姐
I will never visit your house again.
我以後不會再去妳家了
Don't say that!
別那麼說
You and Grandpa are part of our family, too!
妳和外公也是我們的家人
Didn't Kii find a stone for you and place it in the box the other day?
希衣前幾天不是找到妳的石頭 並且放進盒子裡了嗎？
Someone like me is better off gone for everyone's sake.
像我這樣的人最好離開，對大家都好
Please tell Kii to throw away my stone.
請轉告希衣把我的石頭丟掉
Urara really said that?
小麗真的那麼說嗎？
Maybe she's really planning to get married.
也許她真的打算結婚了
Isn't it fine as long as she's happy?
只要她幸福，不是也很好嗎？
The problem is she doesn't look like she's happy.
問題是她看起來不像幸福洋溢的樣子
I don't like it.
我不喜歡這樣
Urara used to smile so much, but it feels like she completely changed.
以前小麗很喜歡笑 可是她最近好像完全變了一個人
But, why did Urara suddenly talk about getting married?
不過小麗為什麼突然提起結婚的事？
I think she really likes you, Dad.
我認為她很喜歡你，爸爸
What?
什麼？
That's why she said she's not coming over.
因此她才說不會再來我們家
No way. That's not possible.
不可能，那是不可能的事
Dad's right. No way at all.
爸爸說得對，完全不可能
Seriously, you should stop talking!
說真的，你別再說話了
Mr. Asuda.
主人
Yes?
什麼事？
Ms. Urara...
小麗小姐…
Do you know something, Mita?
妳知道內情嗎，三田小姐？
No, it's nothing.
不知道，沒什麼
HARUMI HOUSEKEEPING AGENCY
（晴海家政婦介紹所）
Isn't it fine?
這樣不是很好嗎？
If there's something you want to say, just say it.
如果妳有話想說，就直接說出來吧
I mean, you're worried about the family that you're working for.
身為家政婦 替自己工作的家庭感到擔憂
It's a given as a housekeeper.
是很自然的事
Akari. You're beginning to change.
燈子，妳正在改變
You're trying to regain your humanity.
妳逐漸找回妳的人性
It's all thanks to that family.
這一切都要歸功於那個家庭
Even today.
甚至今天
It's the first time you came here to consult me about something.
也是妳第一次來找我商量事情
You told them the pain and sadness you went through.
妳把自己經歷的痛苦和悲傷告訴他們
The fact that you could tell them about it
而妳能對他們說出那些事
is proof that you love them.
就證明了妳愛他們
Oh, my. Didn't I just say something great?
天啊，我是不是說了很不得了的話？
I should write it down.
我應該把這些話寫下來
Hey, why don't you stop this already?
妳也該停止了吧？
Stop thinking that people around you become unhappy
停止那種妳照著妳的意志行事
when you act on your own will.
就會給妳周圍的人帶來不幸的想法吧
Here you go.
來，請吃一個
How are you feeling, Kakeru?
你的身體還好嗎，小翔？
I'm much better now. My fever subsided, too.
我覺得好多了，也退燒了
-That's great. You can talk now, too. -Yeah.
-太好了，你也能說話了 -對
Right. Have you filled up the Parents' Day attendance form, Dad?
對了，爸爸 教學參觀日出席表填好了嗎？
Oh, sorry! Where did I leave it?
抱歉，我把它放在哪裡了？
Pardon me for my impertinence, but I filled it in for you.
請原諒我的無禮，我已經替你填好了
Oh, thanks.
謝謝
Here you go, Kaito.
拿去吧，海斗
Kaito. What about the letter of appreciation?
海斗，那封感謝信怎麼辦？
Parents' Day is tomorrow, right?
明天就是教學參觀日，對吧？
I borrowed Mom's will from Yui to see if I can came up with anything,
我向姐姐借了媽媽的遺書 看看能不能找到靈感
but all I can think of is, "Why did she kill herself?"
但是我只想著，“她為什麼自殺？”
Like I said, Kaito...
正如我說過的，海斗
It's all my fault.
這一切都是我的錯
But, the fact remains that Mom abandoned us.
可是媽媽拋下我們的事實並沒有改變
When she died, all she thought about was your betrayal
她死的時候，只想著爸爸的背叛
and forgot all about us!
完全忘了我們
I just can't accept that.
我無法接受這種事
You're right. It feels as if she just left us to die.
你說得對，讓人感覺她不顧我們死活
As if she didn't care about us anymore.
好像她完全不在乎我們
I wished that she had thought about us and reconsidered her choice.
真希望她能想到我們 並重新考量她的選擇
Maybe... It's all my fault.
可能都是我的錯
It's because I told her to die!
因為我叫她去死
I told you that's not true, Kii.
我說過不是妳的錯，希衣
I don't think I can talk about this in class.
我不覺得我能夠在課堂上談論這件事
I'll write my letter of appreciation to you, Dad.
我還是寫一封給爸爸的感謝信吧
I think that's for the best.
這應該是最好的方式
Well... Okay.
這…好吧
I don't have the right to say anything.
我沒有資格對這件事情發表意見
Man... Is the old hag next door really right?
真是的，隔壁老太婆真的說對了嗎？
That we're not a normal family.
她說我們不是普通的家庭
Please excuse me.
請恕我失禮
What is it?
什麼事？
Hey! What are you doing, Mita?
喂，妳在做什麼，三田小姐？
Please forgive my impertinence,
請原諒我的無禮
but I think you should write the letter of appreciation for your mom.
不過我認為你應該 寫一封給媽媽的感謝信
But... She killed herself.
可是她是自殺的
Your mom did not commit suicide. It was an accident.
你的媽媽並沒有自殺，那是一場意外
-Huh? -What?
-什麼？
Perhaps it's true that your mom wrote a will
你們的媽媽確實留下了遺書
and walked into the river in despair
並且在絕望中走進河裡
to try and kill herself.
企圖自殺
But when she was unable to breathe under the water,
可是當她在水中無法呼吸的時候
she must have thought of this,
她肯定有了這樣的想法
"I don't want to die."
“我不想死
"I must never die, for the sake of my kids."
為了孩子們著想，我絕對不能死”
I'm sure she regretted it.
我確信她感到後悔
That she shouldn't have made this hasty decision.
她後悔自己做出了這個倉促的決定
That she should have had a proper talk with Mr. Asuda again.
她後悔自己沒有再次跟主人好好溝通
That she should have tried to work things out again
她後悔自己沒有為了孩子們
for the children's sake.
努力解決這個難題
What are you saying, Mita?
妳在說什麼，三田小姐？
Yui's right. How do you know that?
是啊，妳怎麼會知道？
It's because I've tried to kill myself before, too.
因為我以前也曾企圖自殺
Contrary to what I want, my body struggled to live by itself.
我的身體違背我的意志 不斷地掙扎，想求生存
I struggled desperately to breathe again.
我拼命地掙扎，想再次呼吸
I'm sure that your mom must have realized it then.
我確信你們的媽媽當時肯定領悟到了
"I want to meet Yui again. I want to see Kakeru again."
“我想再次見到小結，再次見到小翔
"I want to see Kaito again. I want to see Kii again."
再次見到海斗，再次見到希衣”
I'm sure that was all she could think of.
我確信她的腦海中只有這個想法
"I want to teach Yui more about cooking and household chores,
“身為長女的小結如此努力
when she's working so hard as the eldest child."
我想多教教她 準備料理和做家務事的方法
"I want to help Kakeru when he's in trouble,
在小翔面臨困難時，我想幫助他
because he always tries his best to protect the family."
因為他一直拼命守護這個家
"Kaito always does his best in everything.
海斗總是盡全力做好每一件事
I want to praise him more."
我想多誇獎他
"Kii is inquisitive, and always asks questions.
好奇心旺盛的希衣總是提出很多問題
I want to come up with an answer for her to become happy."
我想提供能讓她感到幸福的答案
"I should have talked more to everyone."
我應該和大家多聊聊
"I should have given them more hugs."
我應該多抱抱他們
"I want to meet everyone."
我想見大家
"I want to see them."
我想見他們
"I don't want to die."
我不想死
"I want to hear their voices."
我想聽見他們的聲音
"I want to live."
我想活下去”
So...
因此…
Your mom did not commit suicide.
你們的媽媽並不是自殺的
She died in an accident.
而是死於意外
I'm sure that...
我確信…
she never intended to abandon all of you.
她絕對沒有拋棄你們的想法
But...
可是…
That's not what the others think.
其他人並不是這麼想的
He's right, Mita. Nagiko died because of me--
他說得對，三田小姐 他們的媽媽是因為我才…
It doesn't matter what the others think.
其他人怎麼想並不重要
That is...
這件事…
something you decide for yourselves.
應該由你們自己決定
I...
我…
I don't think Mom killed herself.
我認為媽媽不是自殺的
Me, too.
我也這麼認為
Don't say it before us.
別搶在我們之前說
I'm supposed to be the one writing the letter.
要寫感謝信的人可是我
Dad.
爸爸
Mom's death...
媽媽的死…
was an accident.
是一件意外事故
Right?
對吧？
You're right.
妳說得對
I'm sure Mom must be thinking of the same thing in heaven.
我相信在天國的媽媽 一定也有這種想法
She wants to have this letter burnt.
她想把這封信燒掉
Mita. Do you have a lighter?
三田小姐，妳有打火機嗎？
I do.
有
I'm going to burn it now, okay?
我要開始燒了，可以嗎？
I WOULD RATHER DIE THAN BE ABANDONED BY YOU
（我寧可死了，也不想被你拋棄）
Mr. Asuda.
主人
If there is nothing else,
要是沒有其他事情的話
I will take my leave now.
我就先告辭了
Oh, Mita.
三田小姐
Thank you so much for what you said.
非常感謝妳剛才說的那一番話
I'm sure the kids are grateful for your words, too.
我相信孩子們一定也很感激妳說的話
Just like me.
就跟我一樣
I simply said what I'm thinking of.
我只是說出了我的想法
Mita.
三田小姐
Yes?
什麼事？
I won't think about things that I should have done
我不會再去想 那些我認為過去應該做的事情
or things that I should not have done.
或不應該做的事情
I'll stop harping on the past and my regrets.
我不會再反覆抱怨過往的事情與遺憾
Doing that just denies the present time I'm living in.
那麼做只是否定了 我此時此刻還活著的現實
From now on, I want to live with my children
從現在開始，我要和孩子們一起
and thinking about the present and the future only.
只專注著當下與未來，好好活下去
From now on, I want to talk about Nagiko
從今以後，我會和孩子們
to the kids, as much as possible.
多談談他們母親生前的事
I believe that's what I should do as a father.
我相信這是我身為父親應該做的事情
This is the invoice for today's overtime hours.
這是今天的加班收據
Okay.
好
Please excuse me.
我告辭了
Mita. I wrote the essay, so would you read it?
三田小姐，我的作文寫好了 妳願意看看嗎？
That is...
這件事…
something you should ask your father to do.
應該請你的父親來做
I thought so.
說得對
But will you read it? You can do it tomorrow morning.
不過妳願意看看嗎？明天再看也可以
As you wish.
我知道了
Mita.
三田小姐
Could you please make it for Parents' Day tomorrow? Do it for Kai.
為了海斗，是否可以拜託妳 去參加明天的教學參觀日？
You can treat this as an order.
就算是工作命令吧
Mommy!
媽媽
I'll read you a letter in school tomorrow,
我明天會在幼兒園朗讀寫給媽媽的信
so you have to come, okay?
妳一定要來，好嗎？
Let's see. What did you write, Jun?
讓我看看，你寫了什麼，純？
What's wrong, Mita?
怎麼了，三田小姐？
The moon's beautiful today, Akari.
今晚的月亮很美喔，燈
Hurry up, Mommy!
快點來，媽媽
Mita?
三田小姐？
I'm going to become an astronaut when I grow up.
我長大之後要成為太空人
Is that so?
是嗎？
Then you should take us to the moon one day. Right, Akari?
那麼你以後帶我們去月球 對吧，燈？
Are you fine, Mita?
三田小姐，妳沒事吧？
Mita!
三田小姐
Please excuse me.
我告辭了
You should be fine now, seeing that you have such a good appetite.
你的胃口這麼好，身體應該沒事了
Yeah, I'm back to tip-top condition.
對，我又回到最佳狀態了
-Try not to let your neck get too cold. -Got it.
-別讓脖子受涼了 -好
Kaito. Sorry that I can't make it today.
海斗，抱歉，我今天無法出席
It's fine.
沒關係
I'm done.
我吃飽了
Have a safe trip.
路上小心
-We're leaving, Dad. -Take care.
-我們出門了，媽媽 -小心點
I'm leaving!
我出門了
Mita. Have you read my essay?
三田小姐，妳看過我的作文了嗎？
Yes.
看過了
What do you think?
妳覺得如何？
If you don't hurry up, you will be late.
你不快點的話，會遲到的
Oh no! I'm done!
糟糕，我吃飽了
Listen to my essay later, Mom. I'm leaving.
媽媽，晚點請聽聽我的作文，我走了
-Have a safe trip. -I'm leaving.
-路上小心 -我出門了
Good luck.
加油
Okay! Everyone, don't get nervous just because your mom's here.
好，各位同學 別因為你們的媽媽來了就感到緊張
Just act like how you usually do in class.
大家就跟平常上課一樣就好
Okay. Who's going to start first?
好，誰想最先開始朗讀？
-Me!
-我
Okay, Homura.
好，法村
Okay.
是
"My mom. My mom is an amazing person."
“我的媽媽，我媽媽是個很厲害的人
"She carries stuff heavier than Dad does."
她拿的東西比爸爸拿的還重
"I wake up a few times at night because of Mom's snoring."
我在夜晚有幾次被媽媽的鼾聲吵醒
"But it looked like she was sleeping well,
不過媽媽看起來睡得很香甜
so I decided not to wake her up."
於是我決定不把她叫醒
"When I grow up,
等我長大之後
I want to become a mother just like Mom."
我希望成為像我媽媽那樣的母親”
Okay. I think that essay really expresses how thankful she is towards her mother.
好，我認為這篇作文 充分表達了她對媽媽的感謝之情
A round of applause!
掌聲鼓勵
Who wants to read their essay next?
接下來誰想朗讀作文？
-Me!
-我
Okay, Asuda.
好，阿須田
Yes.
是
"This summer, my mother...
“我的媽媽在今年夏天…
died in an accident."
因為意外而去世了
"I'm the third child of four siblings."
我是四個兄弟姐妹中的老三
"I'm not the first child, not the eldest son, nor the youngest."
我不是老大，不是長子，也不是老么
"So I always asked Mom who she loved the most."
因此我老是問媽媽 四個孩子中，她最喜歡誰
"I wanted her to say that it was me."
我希望聽到她說她最喜歡我
"However, Mom's answer was always the same."
然而媽媽總是回答相同的一句話
"I love everyone of you, of course."
‘當然每個人都一樣喜歡’
"I wasn't happy about that."
她的回答令我感到不開心
"I thought Mom was a cold person."
我覺得媽媽很冷漠
"I didn't care if it was a lie. I wished that she had said it was me."
即使她說謊也好 我希望聽到她說她最喜歡我
"But, now I regret it."
但是我現在很後悔
"I should have been the one telling her that I loved her."
我應該對媽媽說我很愛她
"I should have thanked her, and be grateful towards her."
我應該謝謝她，對她心存感激才對
"If I had done so, maybe Mom wouldn't have died."
如果我當初那麼做 也許媽媽就不會死了
"I'm sure that my siblings feel the same way."
我相信我的兄弟姐妹也有同樣的心情
"Mom, we're sorry that we talked back and always complained about you."
媽媽，對不起 我們老是頂嘴，還不斷抱怨妳
"We're sorry that we never realized how you felt."
很抱歉，我們沒有注意到妳的心情
"You always cooked delicious food for us,
妳總是為我們準備美味的飯菜
but we never thanked you for it. We're sorry."
我們卻從來沒有向妳道謝，真對不起
"If I could meet Mom once again,
如果能再次見到媽媽
I want to eat her favorite apple with her."
我要和媽媽一起吃她最愛吃的蘋果
"Her shoulder were always stiff,
媽媽總覺得肩膀僵硬
"Her hands always get cold when she's washing the dishes,
媽媽的雙手總是因為洗碗盤而變冷
so I want to warm it up for her."
所以我想替她溫暖她的雙手
"I've never done it before when she was still alive,
她還活著的時候，我從未做過這件事
but I want to hug her tight."
但是我想緊緊擁抱她
"She might get mad and say it's too late to say all these,
她可能會生氣 並且說這一切都太遲了
but all of us still love Mom."
不過我們所有人仍然愛著媽媽
"We love her so much."
我們非常愛她
"I'm really glad that I'm born as Mom's son."
我真慶幸能夠成為媽媽的孩子
"And I will continue to live thinking about that."
往後的人生中 我也會抱著這種想法活下去”
Okay. Well... Thank you.
好，那…謝謝你
Then... You're next, Nishiyama.
那麼下一位，西山
Yes.
是
"To Mom. My mom is a scatterbrain…"
“致我的媽媽 我的媽媽是個健忘的人…”
I THINK THIS IS WELL-WRITTEN
（我認為這篇作文寫得很好）
Damn it! I'm so happy!
真是的，我太開心了
Sorry.
對不起
Mita! I'll help you!
三田小姐，我來幫忙
No, I'm fine.
不用了
Please, just let me do something!
拜託妳，讓我也做一點事情吧
Then...
那麼…
Could you stir the bowl?
妳能幫我攪拌那個碗裡的東西嗎？
As you wish.
我知道了
I'm done!
完成了
It's hot! It's so hot!
燙，好燙
It's so painful!
好痛
We're home.
我們回來了
Mita.
三田小姐
I'm truly sorry.
我真的非常抱歉
No, you don't have to apologize anymore.
別這麼說，妳不必再道歉了
Kii only received a minor burn since you did first-aid treatment.
因為妳急救處理得當 希衣只受到輕度燒傷
It's getting late, so you should get home and rest.
時間不早了，妳先回家休息吧
I'm truly sorry.
我真的非常抱歉
Thanks to you, my husband told me to leave the house.
都是妳害的，我老公把我趕出來了
He won't let me have custody of my son, either.
他也不讓我擁有我兒子的監護權
I only meant it as a joke,
我當時只是開玩笑
and you really tried to burn down the house.
沒想到妳卻真的試圖燒了我家
Is it that fun to bring misfortune to other families?
害別人的家庭陷入不幸，很好玩嗎？
You also did something bad to
今天妳也對他們家的小女兒
the youngest child today, right?
做了不好的事，對吧？
I could even hear her cries from my house.
我在我家裡都聽得見她的哭聲
Why don't you realize it?
妳為什麼還不明白？
No matter what you do,
不論妳做什麼
you always make everyone around you unhappy.
妳總是替妳身邊的人帶來不幸
Just disappear somewhere before a disaster really happens!
在嚴重的災難發生之前
Welcome, good afternoon!
歡迎光臨，午安
One family set, please.
請給我一份家庭套餐
Yes. A moment, please!
好的，請稍等
Sorry to keep you waiting.
抱歉，讓妳久等了
Thank you very much.
謝謝光臨
Over here, Akari!
這裡，燈
Hurry up, Mommy!
快點過來，媽媽
Mommy. Let's share a cola together.
媽媽，我們一起喝一杯可樂吧
Here you go.
這個給你
Come on. You should eat, Akari.
快點，妳也吃吧，燈
It's really good, Mommy.
真的很好吃，媽媽
But this is nothing compared to Mommy's cooking, right?
不過還是完全比不上 媽媽的料理，對吧？
Of course!
當然比不上
I'm sorry, Jun.
對不起，純
I'm sorry, dear.
對不起，親愛的
The two of you are angry that
你們兩個在生我的氣
I'm the only one becoming happy, right?
因為只有我一個人過得幸福，對吧？
I'm scared because I feel like I'm starting to love them.
我很害怕，因為我覺得 自己逐漸愛上他們了
I'm scared that they will become unhappy
我很害怕他們會變得不幸
because I'm starting to love them.
因為我開始愛上他們了
So...
所以…
Hurry and take me to where you two are.
快點帶我去你們那邊吧
Mita?
三田小姐
Stop blaming yourself.
別再責怪妳自己了
I'm sure your husband and son doesn't want you to do that!
我相信妳的老公和兒子 也不希望看到妳自責
Haven't you done enough? You should go back to who you were.
妳做的還不夠多嗎？ 妳就做回妳自己吧
I will protect you, Mita!
我會保護妳的，三田小姐
We're begging you!
求求妳
Stop coming here and order things like this already!
別再來這裡點這些食物了
Stop sitting here for hours and look at these things you'll never eat
別來這裡呆坐數小時 看著這些妳永遠不會吃的食物
and be in pain already!
然後陷入痛苦之中
I'm sorry...
不好意思…
but could you leave me alone?
可以請你們別管我嗎？
We can't do that!
我們辦不到
From now on...
從今以後…
We'll eat all of them.
我們會把這些食物都吃光
No matter how many times you come, we'll eat all of them!
不論妳來這裡多少次 我們都會把所有食物吃光
We won't listen to you!
妳別想阻止我們
We'll eat it all, even if it means we'll get a stomachache!
即使吃壞肚子，我們也會吃光
We'll come and eat it all forever, until you finally decide to give up!
我們會一直來這裡把食物吃光 直到妳決定放棄為止
I beg you!
我求求你們
Stop being so nice to me already!
別再對我這麼好
I...
我…
I cannot return to how I once was
我已經無法回到
before my husband and son died!
我老公和小孩去世前的那個我
I'm not allowed to.
我也不准回到那時候的我
We...
我們…
We won't die, even if you love us!
即使擁有妳的愛，也絕對不會死的
No matter how tough it can be, we'll prove to you that we'll be happy!
不論有多麼艱辛，我們都會 向妳證明我們會得到幸福的
So...
所以…
Let's go home together.
我們一起回家吧
Mita!
三田小姐
Let's go back to our home, together.
讓我們一起回到我們的家
Let's go home.
我們回家吧
What do you want, Shota?
你想要什麼，翔太？
A bicycle.
自行車
A bicycle?
自行車？
What's wrong, Mita?
怎麼了，三田小姐？
No, it's nothing.
沒什麼
Mita. Sing with me again.
三田小姐，再和我一起唱歌吧
After climbing up
爬上這座
This slope
山丘之後
There's a tree
往右邊走
to the right
有一棵樹
When you turn at the tree
在樹的地方轉彎
and walk straight
然後繼續前進
Your beloved home is there waiting for you
你可愛的家在等著你
What's wrong, Kakeru?
怎麼了，小翔？
I'm seriously having a stomachache now!
我真的吃壞肚子了
Yikes! I'm not going to make it!
完了，來不及了
Don't you ever dare smile until you die!
妳到死都別再笑了
Excuse me. What did you want to talk about?
不好意思，你想跟我談什麼？
The thing is...
是這樣的…
If you don't mind,
如果妳不介意的話
I would like to go out with you under the pretext of marriage.
我願意以結婚為前提跟妳交往
Are you fine with me?
你覺得我可以嗎？
Yes!
可以
I like your straightforward personality, Ms. Urara.
我喜歡妳的直率個性，麗小姐
Oh... I see.
我明白了
You don't want to?
妳不想跟我交往嗎？
That's not it.
不是這樣的
I'll do as you say.
我會照你的意思去做
Nothing ever works out when I try doing things myself.
每當我照我的意思行事，總是不如願
If you're fine with someone like me...
如果你覺得我可以的話…
Keiichi!
姐夫
Sorry. Do you have a minute, Urara? Sorry about this.
抱歉，請過來一下，小麗，真是抱歉
Wait...
等一下…
Why are you here?
你為什麼會在這裡？
I heard from Mita.
我聽三田小姐說了
Why are you trying to get married to someone you don't even love?
妳為什麼要和一個妳不愛的人結婚？
Kii was really sad that you told her to throw away your stone.
希衣非常難過 因為妳要她把妳的石頭丟掉
Please leave me alone already!
請別再管我了
If you get married like this, it's not nice to the other party!
要是妳就這樣結婚的話 對另一方也不太好吧？
I don't have a choice!
我別無選擇
The person I love is just like the old maid.
我喜歡的那個人是最不適合的人
He's the last person I should get married to.
他是我最不應該嫁的人
What do you mean?
什麼意思？
You see...
是這樣的…
I...
我…
I like you.
喜歡你
What?
什麼？
I've been trying to deny and suppress my feelings for you the entire time.
我一直試圖否認並壓抑對你的感情
But it's not working.
但是完全沒用
The more I do that,
我越是壓抑
the harder I fall for you.
越是喜歡你
You get it already, right? Just leave me be.
你明白了吧？別再管我了
I'm sorry, but could you not stand behind me?
不好意思 可以請你們別站在我的身後嗎？
Is that because it reminds you of your younger brother stalking you?
因為這樣會讓妳想起 妳被妳弟弟跟蹤的事嗎？
Yes.
是的
Okay. We won't do that anymore.
好，我們不會再這麼做了
Mita.
三田小姐
I had a dream that you became Urara.
我曾夢見妳變成小麗
Back then, I wondered why I had that dream.
當時我不明白為什麼會做那個夢
But, I could understand after I got to know more about you.
但是在進一步了解妳之後，我明白了
It must be because you always smiled in the past, just like Urara.
一定是因為妳以前經常笑 就像小麗一樣
Mita...
三田小姐
We have an order.
我們有一項工作命令
What is it?
什麼工作命令？
Forget about it.
忘了吧
Forget that you're told to never smile until you die.
忘了有人告訴妳到死都別再笑的事情
We...
我們…
We want to see you smile.
希望能夠看到妳的笑容
I'll do my best to come up with jokes.
我會努力想出笑話
Me too! I'll make you happy.
我也會努力讓妳開心
From now on, will you smile with us
從今以後，當我們感到開心或快樂時
when we're having fun or when we're happy?
妳願意跟著我們一起笑嗎？
I'm sorry...
很抱歉
but that's the only thing I can't do.
這件事我做不到
If you insist on it,
如果你們堅持要我笑的話
-I will quit-- -Okay, fine!
-我會辭職… -我知道了
Then...
那麼…
You'll do everything we ask
除了笑之外
other than asking you to smile, right?
其他的事情妳都會聽我們的，對吧？
If it is within my means.
只要是我能做到的事情
Then...
那麼…
Stay with us forever.
永遠和我們在一起
I found your stone, Mita.
我找到妳的石頭了，三田小姐
Put it in here, Mita.
把石頭放進來吧，三田小姐
Please...
請妳…
be our mommy.
當我們的媽媽吧
As you wish.
我知道了
THE CONCLUSION IS FINALLY HERE. WILL MITA SHOW HER SMILE...
（最終集來了 三田小姐是否會展露笑容…）
What's wrong, Dad?
怎麼了，爸爸？
Are you all right?
你還好嗎？
Don't mess with me!
別惹我
I'm in your care from now on.
從今以後，請多多指教
Subtitle translation by: Qianni Lu
字幕翻譯：黃琪芳